Guide to the Richard Erdoes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Richard Erdoes papers
1920-2008
1965-1998
WA MSS S-2609
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
171.99
(318 boxes) + 12 cold storage, 5 broadside
Correspondence, writings, audio and moving image recordings, photographic materials, subject files, printed ephemera, art work, and other materials created or collected by Richard Erdoes (1912-2008), author of more than a dozen books about American Indian life. The collection primarily documents Erdoes's activities between 1968 and 1999, and is useful for the study of his writing process and research interests, specifically his work with American Indian individuals and communities. His papers also serve as a resource for the study of the peoples, areas, and subjects that he chose to research and record, and are particularly useful for research about the American Indian civil rights movement, twentieth century American Indian spirituality and religious practices, especially among the Lakota, and American Indian cultural revitilization efforts during the latter half of the twentieth century.
Erdoes, Richard, 1912-2008
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Richard Erdoes on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund and the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1998-1999, and from the Estate of Richard Erdoes on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 317 (electronic disk): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 36-41 (color transparencies): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies are available. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 99-173, 194-199 and 299-313 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Richard Erdoes (1912-2008)
Richard Erdoes, illustrator, photographer, and author of more than a dozen books about American Indian life, was born in Vienna, Austria to Maria Josefa Schrom on July 7, 1912. His father, Richard, was a Hungarian opera singer who had passed away a few months earlier. Upon his birth, his mother joined the household of her sister, the German actress Leopoldine ("Poldi") Sangora. Erdoes spent his childhood surrounded by theatre actors and moving from city to city—Vienna, Berlin, Frankfurt—settling wherever his aunt and her actor husband held lengthy engagements.
When the Nazis came into power in 1933, Erdoes was a student at the Berlin Academy of Art. He established a neighborhood underground newspaper in which he began publishing anti-Hitler cartoons and caricatures. Identified by the Nazis, he fled Germany as a fugitive at the end of 1933, arriving in Austria where he enrolled in the Viennese Kunstgewerbeschule to continue his training. In Austria, Erdoes honed his cartooning skills and supported himself as a caricaturist for Tag and Stunde, two anti-Nazi newspapers. When the Germans entered Austria in 1938, Erdoes fled again, first to Paris, then London, eventually arriving in New York a year later. He married his first wife, Elsie Schulhof (died 1940), shortly after landing in the United States.
Erdoes was welcomed into the German exile community in New York, and launched a successful career as a freelance illustrator and photographer. Over the next two decades, he contributed to publications like National Geographic, American Heritage, Stage Magazine, and Life Magazine; created cover art for record albums; and began illustrating children's books. Erdoes met Jean Sternbergh (died 1995), an art director at Life, in 1945. The couple married in 1950, and had three children— David Richard, Eric Peter, and Jacqueline ("Jaki") Jean.
By the mid-1960s, Erdoes was illustrating and publishing his own children's stories while continuing to build his freelance career. During an assignment to photograph American Indian reservation life for Life, Erdoes became deeply intrigued by contemporary Native American life and spirituality. Outraged by his first-hand experience of conditions on reservations and fascinated by the American Indian belief systems he encountered, Erdoes wrote, illustrated, and edited a number of adult and children's books on American Indian cultures, folklore, and life over the next four decades. He became a passionate advocate for American Indian civil rights, and an avid documenter of tribal life and spiritual revitalization, particularly among the Lakota.
Erdoes and his family opened their apartment in New York City to Lakota visitors and other American Indians during the early 1970s, creating a well-known gathering place for American Indian Movement (AIM) supporters and civil rights activists. Erdoes also became involved in the legal defense of a number of prominent American Indian activists, including Lakota medicine man Leonard Crow Dog, after the 1973 stand-off at Wounded Knee. In 1975, the Erdoes family relocated to Santa Fe where Erdoes continued to write, illustrate, and advocate for Native peoples.
Erdoes's first book about an American Indian tribe was 1967's Pueblo Indians for the Young Readers' Indian Library series. In 1971, he collaborated with John Fire Lame Deer (1903-1976), a Lakota medicine man, on Lame Deer's as-told-to autobiography, Lame Deer: Seeker of Visions. Erdoes published five more as-told-to collaborative narratives with American Indian co-authors: Lakota Woman (1990) and its sequel Ohitka Woman (1993), with Mary Brave Bird; The Gift of Power: The Life and Teachings of a Lakota Medicine Man (1992), with Archie Fire Lame Deer; Crow Dog: Four Generations of Sioux Medicine Men (1995), with Leonard Crow Dog; and Ojibwa Warrior: Dennis Banks and the Rise of the American Indian Movement (2004), with Dennis Banks. Other significant book projects included American Indian Myths and Legends (1984) and American Indian Trickster Tales (1998), both co-edited with Alfonso Ortiz.
Richard Erdoes died on July 16, 2008 in Santa Fe, New Mexico.
Scope and Contents
The Richard Erdoes Papers consist of correspondence, writings, audio and moving image recordings, photographs, subject files, and other materials related to Erdoes's work with and about American Indian peoples, particularly the Rosebud Lakota. The papers span the years 1920 through 2008, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1960s through 1999. Though materials have been arranged primarily by format and function, subjects and topics represented in the collection transcend this organizational system. For instance, individuals who Erdoes recorded and filmed are frequently documented by images in the collection, and in Erdoes's correspondence or subject files.
The papers contain source materials—recordings, photographs, and subject files—which Erdoes used in his "as-told-to" autobiographies and other works about American Indians. Coupled with drafts of his works in Series II, these materials document Erdoes's process of recording, transcribing, and compiling his books. The materials present in the collection are valuable not only as a resource for scholars interested in how Erdoes produced his most famous texts, but also for research about the subjects he documented. Erdoes's relationship with several key figures in the American Indian Movement (AIM) and the Red Power movement of the late 1960s and early 1970s allowed him to document important moments in American Indian civil rights history, including the occupation of Wounded Knee in 1973 and its aftermath. His papers include documents, photographs, posters and other materials related to the trials and imprisonment of Leonard Crow Dog and reveal Erdoes's advocacy efforts on behalf of Crow Dog and other AIM members. American Indian social and political issues are prominent themes in the papers, accompanied by Erdoes's documentation of both the daily life and spiritual practices of the communities and families with whom he worked. The papers are a source for research about twentieth century American Indian spiritual beliefs and traditions; the Native American Church; and American Indian cultural revilization efforts.
Correspondence (Series I.) reveals the Erdoes family's on-going friendships and personal relationships with American Indians, particularly the Crow Dog family, and provides a glimpse of the professional relationships that Erdoes maintained with the editors and publishers of his books. In addition to drafts of many of his works about American Indians and some of this other publishing projects, Series II. Writings includes research notes, film and book proposals, published editions, book reviews, ephemera and other material related to Erdoes's career as an author.
Photographic materials in Series III. consists of tens of thousands of color and black and white images (negatives, 35mm and glass slides, transparencies as well as prints) that Erdoes created or collected. The images primarily document Erdoes's interest and work about the American West and American Indian peoples, but images of his family and various European trips are also present, along with portraits, landscapes, and city scenes that may be representative of Erdoes's commercial work. The images showcase Erdoes's interests and his evolving fascination with different areas and people, tracing his travels and activities over more than forty decades; simultaneously, the organization of the visual materials, with caption information that Erdoes created, reveal connections that Erdoes made among his photographed subjects and in some cases, his understanding of their meaning. In addition to documenting Erdoes's work, the images themselves are a visual resource for the study of American Indian communities-- particularly Navajo (Diné), Pueblo and Lakota communities-- and the American West in the twentieth century. A selection document American Indian civil rights actions and tribal ceremonies. Many of these images are present because of the relationships that Erdoes built with various tribal leaders and medicine men, allowing him access to photograph events that he witnessed and in which he often participated.
Most of the ten 16mm films that comprise the Films series (Series IV.) document the Crow Dog family, recording life and ceremonies on the Rosebud reservation and at Crow Dog's Paradise; footage of Mary Brave Bird and a pan-Indian rights movement gathering are also present. Much of the film is spliced together and unaccompanied by sound.
The recordings in Series V. are a rich trove of audio documentation, consisting of over three hundred individual recordings. Interviews with American Indian individuals, including Erdoes's co-authors, prominent American Indian Movement (AIM) members, elders, and American Indian spiritual and political leaders are present, as are recordings of events, speeches, and ceremonies. Many of the recordings intimately document the perspectives and concerns of twentieth century American Indians in their own words. American Indian spirituality and traditional belief, as well as the practices of the Native American Church, are prominent themes. A Ghost Dance, likely Crow Dog's 1974 Ghost Dance, is particularly well-documented with forty-eight recordings. Other recurring themes include contemporary American Indian social, political, and economic issues, cultural revitalization efforts, and the American Indian Movement (AIM).
Erdoes's subject files (Series VI.) reflect his broad interest in American Indian issues, in particular his interest in contemporary news events. There are substantial subject files associated with Leonard Crow Dog, the American Indian Movement, and the 1973 Occupation of Wounded Knee. The subject files also contain transcripts of some of the audio recordings Erdoes conducted with his co-authors, and transcribed first-hand accounts of various events. Erdoes appears to have used his subject files as a structure to organize his transcripts topically, interfiling sections from various recordings by subject rather than filing transcripts by interviewee or date. A substantial clippings file is also present, and many of the materials in the subject files bear Erdoes's annotations and highlighter markings.
Erdoes's interest in the social and political landscape of American Indians is further documented by newsletters, magazines, fliers, ephemera, and other published materials present (Series VII.). Among these printed works are publications by European American Indian supporters, the American Indian movement, various tribes and tribal councils, American Indian student groups, and pan-Indian organizations; mainstream magazines profiling Native issues are also present. Many of the publications have an explicitly political angle, capturing the genesis, radicalism, and evolution of the American Indian civil rights movement and late twentieth century tribal revitalization efforts.
The papers include Erdoes's collection of broadsides, posters, and art works (Series VIII.) The series includes posters that Erdoes appears to have created for New York City events, as well as art work by Henry Crow Dog, and a series of drawings that are unattributed, but bear close resemblance to Erdoes's illustration style. Together with the photographic materials, film, and subject files, the posters position the Erdoes Papers as a resource for studying the representation and documentation of twentieth century Native peoples, particularly on the Pine Ridge and Rosebud reservations, as well as in Pueblos and other Indian communities in the American Southwest. The posters are also an important companion to the grassroots publications in Series VII; together, these materials showcase American Indian activism and community organization.
The 2010 Addition includes additional writings, photographic material, audiovisual material, posters, ephemera, and artwork that document Erdoes's collaboration with Leonard Crow Dog, Archie Fire Lame Deer, and Dennis Banks, his writings on the American Indian Movement (AIM), and his research on other aspects of Native American culture and history.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1964-1995. II. Writings, 1965-1997. III. Photographic Materials, 1952-1999. IV. Films, circa 1970. V. Audio Recordings, 1964-1996. VI. Subject Files, 1951-1998. VII. Printed Material, 1921-1998. VIII. Posters and Works of Art, 1967. 2010 Addition, 1920-2008.
Dakota Indians; Indians of North America -- Biography -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Civil rights -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Government relations -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Religion -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Rites and ceremonies -- 20th Century; Indians of North America -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Navajo Indians; Peyotism; Pueblo Indians; Pine Ridge Indian Reservation (S.D.); Rosebud Indian Reservation (S.D.); Wounded Knee (S.D.) -- History -- Indian occupation, 1973; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Bumper stickers; Interviews; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographic prints; Posters; Slides (photographs); Sound recordings; German American authors -- 20th Century; Brave Bird, Mary, 1954-2013; Crow Dog, Henry; Crow Dog, Leonard, 1942-; Erdoes, Richard, 1912-2008; Lame Deer, approximately 1903-1976; Lame Deer, Archie Fire, 1935-; Crow Dog family; American Indian Movement; Native American Church of North America
- Correspondence, 1964-1995; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I. Correspondence is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Third-Party Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence in the Richard Erdoes Papers consists primarily of incoming letters to Erdoes and his family from American Indian individuals or correspondence about topics related to Erdoes's work, research, and advocacy for Native Americans.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Correspondence with publishers about specific titles may also be found in Series II. Writings, under the title of the work. Erdoes also often integrated his research and correspondence, which means that additional correspondence is housed in Series VI. Subject Files.
  - General Correspondence
    General Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's last name or the first word in a company title. Letters from correspondents not listed individually have been filed in "letter" general files. Unidentified correspondence has been arranged at the end of the subseries.
    The file folders that Erdoes originally used have been retained in many cases, as they reveal Erdoes's organizational system and occasionally bear additional annotations.
    General Correspondence contains incoming letters, both personal and professional, adressed to Richard Erdoes and his family from American Indian friends and contacts, as well as letters from contacts who assisted with his research and writing about American Indian peoples or assisted with his legal defense efforts for Leonard Crow Dog and others. Drafts and copies of outgoing letters, occasionally on the Erdoes family's illustrated stationary, are also present, though not in great quantities,
    The correspondence reveals Erdoes's relationships, interests, and activities during the last half of his life, shedding light on his friendships with co-authors and their families, revealing generosity towards Indian people he befriended, and highlighting his activist efforts on behalf of American Indian peoples. Letters often relay personal news and reveal the living conditions and experiences of correspondents. A number of fan letters also reveal Erdoes's influence and impact on aspiring writers.
    Correspondence of note includes copies of letters from civil rights lawyer William Kunstler concerning Leonard Crow Dog's legal case; the Erdoes family's multi-generational correspondence with the Crow Dog and Lame Deer families; handwritten letters from Mary Brave Bird to Richard Erdoes; and correspondence from an array of American Indian political and spiritual leaders, activists, and artists.
    - Akwesasne Notes, 1973 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      See also: Rarihokwats
    - American Indian Community House (New York, N.Y.), 1972-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "B" general, 1976, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Banai-Benton, Edward, 1979 October 26, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biggs, Eric R. (DNA-People's Legal Services, Inc.), 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Brave Bird, Mary, 1968-74 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Burnette, Robert, 1967-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Burnette, Lanford, 1977 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Enclosing a letter from Michael R. Tuma, dated 1977 September 16
    - "C" general, 1970 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cassadore, Philip, 1970 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Cody, Iron Eyes, 1972 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cooksey, Andrew, [1992?], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cottonwood, Ron, [1981?] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Crow Dog, Deana, 1984 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Crow Dog, Francine, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Crow Dog, Gertrude, 1976 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Crow Dog, Henry, 1967-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Crow Dog, Leonard
      General note
      See: "Prison Letters"
    - Crow Dog, Mary
      See: Brave Bird, Mary
    - David, B. Alley, 1980 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Defender, Addie, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dills, Barbara, 1978 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Duncan, James, 1995 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Eagle Elk, George, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Emery, Steve, 1993 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - For All My Relations, 1991 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Four Arrows (Group), 1977-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes correspondence from Coyote and Snowbird
    - "G" general, 1976, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Gallery 10, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "H" general, 1982 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hittman, Michael, 1973 March (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hungry Wolf, Adolf, 1985 September 24, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Hunsinger, Ruth, 1964-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - KalMar, Vera, 1986 December (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Kill Enemy, Charlie, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Kimball, Yeffe, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - King, Larry J., undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - King, Mathew H., 1977 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Kunstler, William Moses, 1976 March (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "L" general, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - La Deaux, Antoine "Tony", 1967 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Lame Deer, John Fire, 1968-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 40-42)
      Includes correspondence from other family members, including granddaughter Maxine, and a set of letters from Ida Lame Deer, John Fire's wife, to Jean Erdoes
    - Laraque, Marie-Helene, 1978, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Leading Cloud, Jennie, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Little Tree, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Lopez, Louis; Lopez, Regina, 1983-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Luck, Owen, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "M" general, 1971, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - McAllester, David P., 1972 August 14 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - McGaa, Ed, 1973 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Machukay, Tony, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Millard, Gerald L. "Coke", undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - National Indian Youth Council, Inc., 1975 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - New Wilderness Foundation, 1977 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Niatum, Duane, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "O" general, 1973-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Oohosis (Dwayne Desjarlais), 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "P" general, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Primeaux, Francis, 1968-1983 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "R" general, 1971-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Rarihokwats, 1977-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Russell, Gail, undated
      See: "Pine Ridge - Misc."
    - "S" general, 1968-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Schenk, Amelie, 1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Schwartz, Susan, 1977-1985 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Skyhorse, Paul Durant, 1976 February 15 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Stellman, Martin, 1988 September 20 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Sun Bear, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - "T" general, 1976-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Tukak'teatret (Lemvig, Denmark), 1983-1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Vallelunga, [Kevin?], 1978 November 6 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Walking Badger, Fred, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Welskopf, Elisabeth Charlotte, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - White Plume, Regina, 1975-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Yellow Bird, Bob (AIM New Mexico State Coordinator), 1976 December 25 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    Third Party Correspodence is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the sender.
    - Brooke, Edward W. to Sanford J. Rosen (photocopy), 1978 August 4 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      With photocopied TLS from John R. Stanish, US Dept of Justice, to Senator Brooke, dated 1978 June 30
    - Floyd, Elbert to Addie Defender, 1969 April 2 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Josephy Jr., Alvin M. to "Dorrie," American Heritage Publishing Company (photocopy), 1976 April 27 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - National Assembly of Religious Women to Mary Brave Bird, 1992 January 16 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Rosen, Sanford J. to Leonard Crow Dog (photocopy), 1978 August 17 (Box 3, Folder 80)
- Writings, 1965-1997; Series II; 9.59; (23 boxes)
  Series II. Writings, is organized into four subseries: Books, Proposals, Other Writings, and Writings of Others.